I may be a bit late to the party, but I
did bring my favorite whiskey to share.
And the party is the CAC party or the
coronary artery calcium party. And it
took social media by storm a few years
ago already. But while many health
influencers have been urging their
viewers to put immense faith in this one
test to assess their risk of dying from
heart problems, the reality is a bit
more sobering. In fact, in my own
community and in emails that I receive,
I've had people tell me that they have a
CAC score of zero, which should be
exclaimed with pride because it is a
good thing, but it isn't absolution from
coronary artery disease. In this video,
I'd like to walk you through six studies
on the coronary artery calcium test and
why we should sober our interpretations
of it, including why a CAC score of zero
isn't a free health pass and why a high
CAC score may be better than a low CAC
score, as weird as that sounds. In
addition, I'd like to introduce you to a
better test, a more predictive test to
your risk of heart related death. If
you're not familiar, though I imagine
most of you are if you've clicked on
this video, a coronary artery calcium
test is a literal image and assessment
of calcium deposits found in and around
your coronary arteries. The arteries
feeding your heart blood, thereby
nutrients and oxygen and the like.
Generally, the progression goes
something like this. And FYI, this comes
from this scientific review. Generally,
your artery wall thickens as it begins
filling with fats and cholesterol
particles. Then there's usually a
mixture of immune cells among other
cells that infiltrate and often die in
the plaque buildup in the artery wall.
During this process, you can have some
calcium that gets deposited creating a
mixture of cholesterol cells uh other
proteins and calcium. Then as the plaque
develops, it also develops a necrotic
core which is especially dense with dead
immune cells and is usually capped with
a protein cap called a fibrous cap. Then
in the final stages, cells release
enough calcium to create sheets of
calcium across the plaque. This is a
simplistic explanation as the review
goes into more detail on the different
types of cells and their involvement as
well as the release of vesicles that
start this process and more. But we get
the general evolution of calcium and
plaque. Now, by that description, you've
probably noticed that plaque is usually
present before or around the same time
as calcium. So, it stands to reason that
if your coronary artery calcium score is
zero, that's indicating no calcium in
and around your arteries, therefore
there is no plaque. This is how it's
often communicated across social media
as if a zero score is a stamp of no
risk. I think uh Dr. Peter describes
this quite well. Um my problem is not
with the calcium score. with sort of a
school of thought that says, well, a
calcium score if it's zero means nothing
matters. You know, you're sort of
scot-free. And that's, you know,
unfortunately that's just categorically
untrue. And the data bear that out. So a
negative calcium score meaning a a
calcium score of zero absolutely means
actuarially at the population level a
lower risk of a coronary event. And when
we say coronary event, we're the term
mace is what we use to describe it. ma a
major adverse coronary event or cardiac
event. So, heart attack, stroke, or
cardiac death. Um, but it's not zero.
He's right. And we see that in studies
like this where coronary events are
quantified in people with a low CAC
score or a score of zero shown here.
Essentially, if the lines go down, that
means that some people out of the 4,000
asymptomatic people followed up on
experienced a coronary heart disease
event like a heart attack. Keep in mind
these people are asymptomatic. They do
not have any symptoms of heart disease.
In addition, the red line is people with
a very low CAC score and the blue is the
line with people with a CAC score of
zero. Unlike many other data comparisons
on physionic, we actually aren't that
interested in the difference between
these lines. We're more interested in
the fact that the blue line, the people
with a perfect or as Dr. IAS stated
negative CAC score experience heart
disease events if they were perfectly
protected. The blue line would never dip
down. Add on top of that that this study
only followed people for around four
years. So a relatively short period of
time. This is also corroborated in other
studies as well where CAC of zero in
other groups also still shows risk for
some. Now all this leads us to a better
test which we'll get to shortly. This
all leads to the conclusion that a CAC
of zero while a great sign is not a free
pass some people consider it to be.
There is still risk. That raises this
question of well then why? I mean if
calcium tracks with plaque in our
arteries why would a CAC of zero not be
a perfect test for future cardiovascular
disease? Well there's actually a few
reasons. One of them is that the way
that the coronary artery calcium score
according to our initial review is
analyzed it is a combination of the
volume so the size and the density of
the calcium deposit. One can actually be
beneficial to our health all else equal
and the other tends to track with worse
cardiovascular outcomes. Having more
plaque volume is generally seen as a bad
thing. Yet having more density can be
seen as a good thing. So when combining
both of these criteria, you'll get a CAC
score that may not be fully reflective
of the true risk. In fact, speaking of
true risk, there are molecules in drugs
that stabilize plaque, meaning that they
reduce the unstable necrotic core that
we briefly discussed earlier, and they
accelerate the calcification. This is a
net benefit because the dangerous soft
plaque is then stabilized. Although the
CAC score may suddenly shoot up which
might be interpreted altogether as a bad
thing which may not be fair in that
scenario as the alternative would be to
have a low or zero CAC score but have
significant unstable plaque. So speaking
to that further, the risk is not in
highly densely calcified plaque which
would register as a greater CAC score
but in a low density calcified plaque as
the non-calcified plaque is more prone
to rupture and create clots that block
the blood flow in downstream blood
vessels. Now in the end the point is
context matters. Low or high CAC score
does not automatically mean low or high
risk. Still, in general, a low CAC score
is a great sign. However, it's probably
only a great sign in the context of
other risk factors. If you have a CAC of
zero, but you're overweight, you smoke,
you're diabetic, and so on, then a CAC
of zero may actually be a bit worrisome
instead of positive news. However, if
you have a CAC of zero and you take care
of yourself, your blood labs look normal
and so on, the CAC score is likely an
additional good sign. Like I said,
context really matters. Okay, then we've
discussed how interpreting a low or high
CAC score is highly context dependent,
though generally a low or zero CAC score
is a good sign. But then what might be a
better test? Let's get into that next.
Before that, if you're interested in
more detailed breakdown of the
mechanisms of calcium deposits or blood
markers that track with a CAC score or
how age affects what we've been
discussing here and even more around
this next test that we're about to go
over, be sure to check out the full
version of this video that you're
currently watching. It comes with an
accompanying article, a one paragraph
summary of the main points and more. And
it's part of the Physionic Insiders
research review. And you get all these
perks right over here, like live
sessions with me. If you're interested
in my entire catalog of analyses
delivered to your inbox, videos,
articles, podcast, product
recommendations, and more, consider
becoming a Physionic Insider. The link
to join is in the description. Anyway,
this other test is known as a
lowattenuation plaque burden or as you
might have heard of it as a CCTA, a
contrast coronary CT angioraph. This
type of test is superior to the coronary
artery calcium test because it includes
soft plaque, the actual plaque that
causes harm like in this image where the
orange is highlighting the soft plaque
in the artery. That soft plaque is also
called low attenuation, hence the funky
name. So instead of measuring the
calcium that tracks with plaque, but as
we discussed may not always appear in
plaque, which yields these potentially
misleading results, you'd be measuring
the plaque itself. plus a CCTA can also
identify calcified plaque as well. So
it's a more complete picture and
measuring low attenuation plaque tends
to be uh more robust in predicting risk.
An additional advantage of measuring
soft plaque over calcified calcified
plaque is the reversability of soft
plaque. Generally it's considered easier
to reverse soft this like mushy plaque
compared to hardened plaque. So, you
aren't just getting a better indication
of your risk, but you also get a better
idea of what can be reversed. Now, I
realize that was a lot of context and a
lot of science applied to something that
you may have initially thought was super
simple. I have a score of zero on this
bad thing, so I'm good to go. And then
the mean scientist comes in and tells
you that there's more to it than that.
So, I feel responsible for a bit of
clarity so you don't leave mean comments
because you're upset with my fancy
unwanted complications. This is how I'd
think about CAC score. First, if you can
opt for a CCTA test over a pure CAC
test, it's better. But I also understand
that isn't always possible. So, if you
do a CAC score, uh, use a two-step
approach. Step one, is my score low? Is
it near zero? If yes, great. Step two,
if I have a score of zero, what do my
other health metrics look like? If I
have a score of zero in spite of
smoking, being overweight, not being
physically active, working a stressful
job, having a high blood pressure, and
or having poor blood tests, then the
zero should be downgraded in its ability
to wash away worry. It is not
necessarily accurate to your real plaque
status. On the other hand, if you have a
score of zero and you're doing well in
all the previous risk factors and
others, then the zero score is probably
real and comforting. It probably still
isn't a perfect prediction, but your
risk is probably very low. Like I said,
context matters. Anyway, if you're
interested in more on your health, I'm
happy to annoy you further right here.
Thanks for tuning in. I appreciate it.
I'll catch you in the next one. See you.